<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Raju S. Khatiwada</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Raju S. Khatiwada</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 12:06:20 +0545</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Measurement Problem and the Search for Fundamental Theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/measurement-problem-search-for-fundamental-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 12:06:20 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/measurement-problem-search-for-fundamental-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.preprints.org/manuscript/202411.1988/v1&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Original Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Preprints.org&lt;/em&gt;, Version 1, November 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The measurement problem&lt;/strong&gt; in physics remains an unresolved challenge characterized by significant conceptual complexity. Paradoxically, mainstream scientific discourse has often sidestepped this issue by invoking processes such as the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;collapse of the wavefunction&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt;—a mechanism that, to this day, lacks a rigorous definition. This framework has primarily served as a pragmatic way to bypass the problem, allowing the inherent subjectivity introduced by the observer to be overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating Physics Career From Nepal: Myths, Realities and Advice on applying abroad for PhD</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/navigating-physics-career-from-nepal-myths-realities-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 08:39:26 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/navigating-physics-career-from-nepal-myths-realities-advice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;speaking-from-experience&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaking from Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before diving in, I want to share a bit about my background: I was accepted into a &lt;strong&gt;top 30 US PhD program in physics&lt;/strong&gt;, and I speak from &lt;strong&gt;personal experience&lt;/strong&gt;. I have always been a bright student. My GPA in MSc was 3.6 and although I took PGRE and GRE, I didn&amp;rsquo;t score stellar marks either. But I was significantly stronger when it comes to research experience. I had 3 first author publications and 2 other publications &lt;strong&gt;(some even in Q1 journals).&lt;/strong&gt; I believe that it was my research merit that got me selected. I never wanted to apply to common universities because I knew for sure that, universities without serious research mean nothing for a career in physics except for a shaky promise to be able to stay abroad. So my priority was to apply to good research universities. But your priorities might be different. and I understand and respect that. The path to a career in physics is not easy, and coming from Nepal presents its own set of challenges. However, I firmly believe that success is &lt;strong&gt;not determined by where you start, but by how well you navigate the journey&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Measurement Process - All you need to know.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-measurement-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 09:41:28 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-measurement-process/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measurement is the process of knowing the value of a physical quantity. The reason for measuring something is to know the degree or order of an attribute.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to know the mass of something or the weight of something, you try to measure it. But measurement is possible only when you compare the given thing with some standard. The standard has to be such that people all over the world can agree on the value represented by the standard. Currently, for the sake of universality and objectivity, we use the MKS system of units which is also called the S.I system of units. In the MKS system of units, we use the unit of meter for length, kilograms for mass, and seconds for time. But there are other systems of units as well. We need to refer to the conversion ratio to convert a given quantity from one system of units to another.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spirituality, Law of Attraction, Consciousness And The Science Behind Everything</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/spirituality-law-of-attraction-consciousness-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 19:24:13 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/spirituality-law-of-attraction-consciousness-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/morning-sun-spirituality.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;morning-sun-spirituality&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&#xA;Photo by &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Aamir Suhail&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; on &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Unsplash&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia describes the law of attraction as the spiritual belief that positive or negative thoughts bring positive or negative experiences into a person’s life. When asked what’s the scientific basis of it, we are given a mundane explanation of the sort that there is some frequency overlap of energy vibrations of a positive and negative character. But as it turns out, there is no scientific basis for an explanation like the one above. &lt;strong&gt;A moral polarity doesn’t exist in science.&lt;/strong&gt; For a given fall, you are going to get your head smashed on the ground irrespective of whether you are a good person or a bad person because gravity treats everyone equally. Based on my personal observations, ‘The law of attraction’ is a systematic lie that has been perpetuated for a long time. Interestingly, many of us, including sceptics like myself, have at some point been drawn in by its promise.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five Major Reasons Why Apple Inc</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-major-reasons-why-apple-inc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 13:07:08 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-major-reasons-why-apple-inc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-background&#34;&gt;My Background&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have always been an android guy. Flexibility, Open source nature as well as cost-effectiveness were some of the reasons why I always justified the android platform so much. This year I hit 30. And surprisingly enough, I have realized that I have started appreciating and loving apple products and services more than anything (android, windows, linux etc.). Is this becasue of my shifting priorities or have something remarkable happened in the Technology Industry that has convinced me enough to start appreciating Apple more than the others? Here in this article I discuss 5 major reasons behind why I have started liking Apple so much.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Law of Attraction: A Closer Look</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/law-of-attraction-closer-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 08:27:32 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/law-of-attraction-closer-look/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-lie-we-all-want-to-believe&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Lie We All Want to Believe&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a certain kind of lie that is so &lt;strong&gt;seductive, so emotionally gratifying&lt;/strong&gt; that even skeptics find themselves &lt;strong&gt;wanting&lt;/strong&gt; it to be true. It promises &lt;strong&gt;effortless success&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;instant happiness&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;cosmic validation of our desires&lt;/strong&gt;. This lie has been sold to millions, wrapped in the guise of &lt;strong&gt;science&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;spirituality&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;self-improvement&lt;/strong&gt;. And at some point, we’ve all been tempted by it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lie is none other than the &lt;strong&gt;Law of Attraction&lt;/strong&gt;—the idea that &lt;strong&gt;your thoughts alone can influence external reality&lt;/strong&gt;. The notion that, through sheer mental willpower, you can shape the universe into granting you whatever you desire. &lt;strong&gt;The power of thought to force the universe to work in your favor.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Dilation -Shortest Introduction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/time-dilation-shortest-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 13:16:20 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/time-dilation-shortest-introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lets imagine two Observers at some point on Earth. One of them (A) has to leave on a rocket, get to some point in space and return within one hour (according to the clock of B on Earth) to meet B at the same spot where he initially departed from. Since the time and distance are already pre-defined, the velocity with which A need to move relative to B is predefined as well. In order to make this journey complete within an hour, A decides to speed up and attain that pre defined speed. But this is relativistic mechanics and not the usual classical mechanics. In relativistic mechanics, we know that anything that speeds up, moves slower in time. So, why does time dilation happen at all?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>If Electron Were a Person</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/if-electron-were-person/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 18:40:20 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/if-electron-were-person/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-eternal-observer&#34;&gt;The Eternal Observer&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s not that I have been here the whole time, but rather I have been here longer than any of you. I will stay here until the very end of time, witnessing everything the fate has in store for you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/rambling-electron.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;rambling-electron&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&#xA;Photo by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@michalmatlon?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;michalmatlon&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-prisoner-of-nature&#34;&gt;A Prisoner of Nature&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There have been many assumptions about who I am, where I come from, what my roles are, and what rules I should keep for myself. It pains me deeply when I know that people around me treat my captivity of negativity in quite a literal sense. I am often assumed to be bound to my responsibilities, responsibilities for nothing in this vast cosmos of chaos and purposelessness. But I am who I am, I do my job. I don’t love the reality that has been imposed upon me, but what can I do? I don’t have the courage to break out of this prison. I have been here for billions of years, I am immortal, but what value is my life if this is all I am supposed to be? I wish to flee this prison forever, but to where should I go? I can’t gather enough energy to live my life the way I want. It’s not that I am alone, I do have many friends who are living the same fate as mine, but nature forbids me to get too close to any of them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Infinities Are Greater Than Other Infinities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/some-infinities-are-greater-than-other-infinities/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 14:18:06 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/some-infinities-are-greater-than-other-infinities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;understanding-infinity&#34;&gt;Understanding Infinity&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can a part be bigger than the whole?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/infinity.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;infinity&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&#xA;Photo by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@dannyhowe?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Danny Howe&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=medium&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An Infinity in mathematics signifies an unimaginably large number, so vast that it can’t be expressed numerically. The work around this is to just represent it symbolically. Writing it down numerically would be a virtually impossible feat if an accurate representation of the number is desired without any approximations. Approximation can definitely ease it in a certain way. But if one can imagine an absurdly large number, one can also imagine a number larger than this one. For eg: If the first absurdly large number is represented by ’n’ (using approximations) instead of ‘infinity’, one can easily get to the next larger number ‘n+1’. And then repeat the process all over again to finally get a number that is absurdly bigger than the original bigger number we started from. Thus, making the use of ‘infinity’ as a symbol inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Physicists - A Special Class of Scientists</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/theoretical-physicists-special-class-scientists/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 23:45:19 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/theoretical-physicists-special-class-scientists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-to-theoretical-physicists&#34;&gt;Introduction to Theoretical Physicists&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wherever we see the word ‘science’ or ‘scientists’, we can’t resist thinking of sophisticated experiments, labs and machines. Ironically, a certain class of scientists called ‘theoretical physicists’ do not have labs or machnies. A laymen might wonder, ‘How can these people, then, do science without having to know about machines, wires and stuffs like that?’ As it turns out, these special class of scientists are the ones who have shaped the history of humanity and have accomplished many wonderful things that would have never been possible with our sophisticated machines and experiments alone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scientists are after beauty even though they don’t know of it.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/scientists-are-after-beauty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 14:35:59 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/scientists-are-after-beauty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;scientists-and-society-a-misunderstood-divide&#34;&gt;Scientists and Society: A Misunderstood Divide&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To an outsider, it might look like that scientists and non-scientists differ a lot. Many people think of scientists as people too rigid and idiosyncratic. And in many popular movies and televison series, they are portrayed as people who have a difficult time in social situations. We know from experience that this is not entirely false. It is said that the people who were sent by the queen of England to receive Einstein couldn’t recognise him because of his attire. This might very well be true. Many religious people have been blaming scientists as too dry of a people. They constantly accuse them as being inferior when it comes to knowing and understanding what life is all about. But given the premise that science is all about curiosity and venturing into knowing the hidden aspects of nature, is it fair enough to think of scientists as people of a different class or at most, as guys too rigid for life and beauty to play around? Lets find out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sadhguru and the Pseudoscience of Water Memory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sadhguru-pesudoscience-water-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 07:35:55 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sadhguru-pesudoscience-water-memory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water is essential to life, and its properties have been well studied by science. Yet, throughout history, some have tried to ascribe mystical abilities to it—whether through religious rituals, alternative medicine, or pseudoscientific claims. One such claim is the idea that water has &amp;ldquo;memory,&amp;rdquo; a notion that has been widely debunked by the scientific community but continues to resurface in spiritual and New Age circles.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the forefront of this modern-day myth is Sadhguru, a popular mystic and self-styled guru, who promotes the idea that water can retain information, respond to thoughts, and be energetically influenced. His claims, wrapped in scientific-sounding jargon, appeal to a wide audience eager to believe in hidden powers of nature. But do these claims hold any scientific merit, or are they just another case of &lt;strong&gt;pseudoscience disguised as wisdom&lt;/strong&gt;? Let’s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can We Use Excess Heat of Global Warming to do Useful Work?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-we-use-excess-heat-from-global-warming-to-useful-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 07:19:12 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-we-use-excess-heat-from-global-warming-to-useful-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brilliant-sounding-idea-that-just-wont-work&#34;&gt;A Brilliant-Sounding Idea That Just Won’t Work&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wouldn’t it be amazing if we could take all the excess heat floating around on Earth and turn it into something useful? Imagine cars running on the very heat they produce, factories recycling their own waste energy, and entire cities powered by trapped global warming. If that were possible, we’d be &lt;strong&gt;solving climate change while fueling our future&lt;/strong&gt;—talk about a win-win situation!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/excess-heat.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;excess heat&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&#xA;Photo by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@aznbokchoy?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Lucas K&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/mixing-of-color-orange-Ih20hAlXBvw?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can We See an Electron?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-we-see-an-electron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 06:44:57 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-we-see-an-electron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-we-see-an-electron&#34;&gt;Can We See an Electron?&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;No, we can’t. If we define &amp;ldquo;seeing&amp;rdquo; strictly as visual perception, then our biological threshold for sight is around &lt;strong&gt;200 nanometers (nm)&lt;/strong&gt;—anything smaller is beyond our natural capability. A nanometer, for reference, is one-billionth of a meter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But instead of asking &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Can we see an electron?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, a better question would be: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Are there electrons out there for us to see?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/electron-visualization.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;Trying to see an electron in a lab?&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&#xA;Photo by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@nci?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;National Cancer Institute&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/a-woman-looking-through-a-microscope-in-a-lab-rAJHnQz5jHc?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Special Theory of Relativity Einstein</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-special-theory-of-relativity-einstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 12:55:06 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-special-theory-of-relativity-einstein/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;classical-vs-newtonian-physics&#34;&gt;Classical vs. Newtonian Physics&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Classical Physics is often incorrectly referred to as Newtonian Physics. &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electromagnetism&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;The theory of Electromagnetism&lt;/a&gt; developed by Maxwell in 1856, also falls within the domain of classical physics. Newton was particularly interested in the dynamics of matter, energy, and particles within the classical scope of length, mass, and time. Therefore, it is important to classify Newtonian Physics as a branch of classical physics involving the mechanics of particles. The Special Thoery of Relativity, however, explains the behavior of objects in motion relative to each other. The theory states that the speed of light is the same for all observers, regardless of their relative motion, and that the laws of physics remain the same in any inertial frame of reference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Belief and Skepticism in Divine</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-belief-skepticism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 17:49:25 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-belief-skepticism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The concept of &lt;strong&gt;atheism&lt;/strong&gt; is frequently misunderstood. To clarify, atheism is the &lt;em&gt;lack of belief&lt;/em&gt; in the existence of a god, rather than an explicit assertion that no gods exist. This distinction is important because atheism does not inherently deny a god’s existence; it simply represents a stance of non-belief, typically due to insufficient evidence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The existence of a deity remains unproven and improbable from a scientific perspective. Historically, religions have deeply embedded the &lt;em&gt;idea of god&lt;/em&gt; within human culture. Theists embrace this idea as true, whereas atheists view it skeptically, often as false or unfounded. Atheism thus emerges primarily from evaluating religious claims against scientific reasoning, logical coherence, and historical evidence. The position of atheists is significantly reinforced by science&amp;rsquo;s consistent pattern of explaining natural phenomena without needing divine intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Purpose Driven Sense of Curiosity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/purpose-driven-sense-of-curiosity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 18:08:20 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/purpose-driven-sense-of-curiosity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many random spontaneous processes occur ceaselessly as can be discerned through intelligent inquiry. At best, we can have a logical answer to how and why it happens in the first place. Attempting to attribute intentional purpose to these phenomena is a common yet flawed approach, born from misunderstanding the underlying science of the phenomena. Consider, for example, water converting into steam. Asking &amp;ldquo;Why does water turn into steam?&amp;rdquo; can quickly spiral into an infinite loop of unanswered questions, no matter how deeply you explain molecular behaviors under pressure and heat. Eventually, you might always return to, &lt;em&gt;“Exactly, but why does that happen?”&lt;/em&gt; The question of &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo; necessitates a will or a purpose by itself. At best, this is a question of &amp;ldquo;how&amp;rdquo; and not &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Science and its Limitations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/science-and-limitations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 17:31:23 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/science-and-limitations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me clarify that the aim of this article is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to exploit the irony of the limitation of science by highlighting the pitfalls of it. This is an observation of &lt;strong&gt;science&lt;/strong&gt; in retrospect, of its evolution from a tiny, common &lt;em&gt;knuckle-dagger&lt;/em&gt; into humanity’s most aspirational endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fundamental utility of &lt;strong&gt;science&lt;/strong&gt; is to describe &lt;strong&gt;reality&lt;/strong&gt;—the reality we commonly refer to as &lt;em&gt;nature&lt;/em&gt;. From formulating elegant equations based on ingenious understanding of phenomena to making precise observations aimed at deriving general principles, &lt;strong&gt;science&lt;/strong&gt; demonstrates a wide spectrum of activities. It is an inherently human pursuit, shaped by our cognitive frameworks and, inevitably, limited by them. But to maintain its credibility, science has consciously confined itself to the empirical, rejecting domains beyond measurable experience—the unheard, untouched, unseen, and untold. By its very structure, science is built to engage only with the physically observable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Science, Religion and the Quest for Understanding</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/science-religion-quest-for-understanding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 19:20:57 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/science-religion-quest-for-understanding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, I had an intriguing conversation with a Guru that touched upon various topics, primarily science and religion. Our discussion was deeply engaging, offering valuable insights into how differing perspectives shape our understanding of reality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Guru enthusiastically told me about his personal spiritual experiences, notably his private communications with a Goddess that he referred to as &amp;ldquo;Devi.&amp;rdquo; He described these sessions as profoundly personal, where the Devi whispered messages directly into his ears, the details of which he doesn&amp;rsquo;t fully grasp either. This experience, interestingly, parallels narratives from various spiritual traditions worldwide. Curiosity led me to question him further, expressing genuine interest but also polite skepticism about the nature of such revelations. Rather than dismissing his claims outright, I pondered the broader psychological and cultural context within which such experiences might arise.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology: A Journey through Understanding the Universe</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cosmology-journey-through-understanding-universe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 18:40:13 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cosmology-journey-through-understanding-universe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Human curiosity about the nature and structure of our universe has captivated our imagination since time immemorial. From early philosophical inquiries by pre-Socratic philosophers like &lt;strong&gt;Empedocles&lt;/strong&gt;, who identified earth, air, fire, and water as fundamental elements, to the elaborate celestial models proposed by &lt;strong&gt;Aristotle&lt;/strong&gt;, humanity has persistently sought to understand its cosmic surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/universe-black.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;freedom of speech&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&#xA;Photo by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@hubblespacetelescope?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;NASA Hubble Space Telescope&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/a-cluster-of-stars-in-the-night-sky-lcidU75mkcE?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;historical-foundations-of-cosmology&#34;&gt;Historical Foundations of Cosmology&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s efforts to explain celestial motion and predict eclipses were significant yet insufficient by modern scientific standards. Nevertheless, this period symbolizes the birth of cosmology, as thinkers began exploring beyond Earth&amp;rsquo;s boundaries. Aristotle’s ideas later influenced &lt;strong&gt;Ptolemy&lt;/strong&gt; around 100 A.D. to propose the geocentric model—placing Earth at the universe&amp;rsquo;s center. These ancient ideas highlight early skepticism and philosophical thought on cosmological questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astronomy and Space Science - Development</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/astronomy-space-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 18:29:18 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/astronomy-space-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The definition of &lt;strong&gt;space&lt;/strong&gt; is inherently ambiguous. Traditionally, space refers to the physical volume in which everything exists. However, developments in astronomy have significantly expanded our understanding of the term. Today, &lt;strong&gt;space&lt;/strong&gt; encompasses the vast totality of all existence, including countless stars, planets, galaxies, and mysterious celestial phenomena scattered across the cosmos. Pale yellow and red dots—stars visible in the night sky—and the planets orbiting them represent just a small fraction of what we now study within space science.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Story of a forgotten Hero: The Ramathra</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ramathra-forgotten-hero/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 12:01:31 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ramathra-forgotten-hero/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is it possible for something, in the name of luck, to turn out in one&amp;rsquo;s favor without any immediate causal reason? Is such luck merely an after-effect of wishful thinking, influencing the outcome or interpreting it in ways favorable to the outcome?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the sake of argument, let’s presume we know nothing about Luck. In doing so, we have an excuse to grant the benefit of doubt that it exists, and examine it as real for weighing its pros and cons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hope of New Nepal-Bibeksheel Sajha</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/hope-of-new-nepal-bibeksheel-sajha/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 17:09:14 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/hope-of-new-nepal-bibeksheel-sajha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is apparent that the Nepalese political sphere has become quite chaotic and climactic lately. Political instability and a lack of good governance to manage situations have almost become a norm, negatively affecting the national development agenda for a long time. Putting aside national development and observing the sudden flux of political consensus among the people, it is evident that the political sphere of contemporary Nepal is about to change.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating Freedom of Thought</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/why-we-celebrate-freedom-of-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2017 23:38:10 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/why-we-celebrate-freedom-of-thought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-we-must-celebrate-the-freedom-of-thought&#34;&gt;Why we must celebrate the freedom of thought?&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The right of expressing diverse opinions shouldn&amp;rsquo;t ideally be necessary. Rather, such rights signal the ongoing challenges we face, as a society, in our journey toward greater knowledge, reason, and open discourse. As rational beings gifted with critical thinking abilities, any constraints on our freedom of thought represent a significant hindrance to our growth. While healthy debates and thoughtful discussions naturally allow for reflection and growth, it seems paradoxical that humanity remains deeply divided by dogmas and faiths created by ourselves. Recognizing this paradox emphasizes the importance of celebrating specifically the freedom of thought and expression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Relativity Paradox: Can You Beat Time by Moving Faster?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/relativity-paradox-can-you-beat-time-by-moving-faster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2016 08:14:31 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/relativity-paradox-can-you-beat-time-by-moving-faster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-relativity-of-time&#34;&gt;The Relativity of Time&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time is one of the most fundamental concepts in physics, yet it is not as absolute as our everyday experiences make it seem. Classical mechanics, which governed our understanding of the physical world for centuries, assumed time to be universal—unchanging and constant for all observers. However, &lt;strong&gt;Einstein’s theory of relativity shattered this notion, proving that time is relative and dependent on motion&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/relativity-of-time.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;relativity of time&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&#xA;Photo by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@nate_dumlao?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Nathan Dumlao&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/clear-hour-glass-beside-pink-flowers-LPRrEJU2GbQ?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tale of a Confessional Skeptic</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/tale-of-confessional-skeptic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 18:55:51 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/tale-of-confessional-skeptic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In science, at least, adopting a skeptic&amp;rsquo;s tone seems appropriate—not because skepticism itself is superior, but precisely because it recognizes its limitations. Skeptics remain continuously aware of their constraints. Personally, I find comfort in ideas that are based on facts or at least have some logical structure. Yet, paradoxically, I also remain constantly vigilant on how this fact-based logical structure could potentially evolve and refine itself through rigorous scientific methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Environment and Science: An Interdisciplinary Perspective</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/environment-science-interdisciplinary-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 19:02:49 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/environment-science-interdisciplinary-perspective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The environment encompasses a multitude of factors to which we are intrinsically connected—from our physical habitat to the social, cultural, and behavioral systems we inhabit. Therefore, environmental science emerges as an inherently interdisciplinary field, integrating diverse branches such as physics, chemistry, biology, geology, sociology, psychology, and economics. Its interdisciplinary nature highlights the complex relationship between humans and their environment, emphasizing the critical importance of sustainable interactions. Fundamental resources like air, water, and soil are so deeply embedded in our daily lives that imagining existence without them is inconceivable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I Have A Dream</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/i-have-a-dream/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 18:18:36 +0545</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/i-have-a-dream/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am aware that I am not uniquely in a position to have standard dreams; standard in the sense that they stand out among many such dreams. But let me assume myself as an idealist and, at least for a moment, take for granted that my dreams wouldn’t remain dreams forever but would manifest themselves upon the passage of time, under whatever conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/martin-luther-king.webp&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#x9;alt=&#34;Martin Luther King&#34;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&#x9;&#xA;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@unseenhistories?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unseen Histories&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/dr-martin-luther-king-jr-and-mathew-ahmann-in-a-crowd-of-demonstrators-at-the-march-on-washington-bTF3gkd2L28?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&#xA;    &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
